<task id="gaia-workflow-engine" name="GAIA Workflow Engine" internal="true">

<objective>
Universal workflow execution engine for GAIA. Loads workflow.yaml configs,
resolves variables, processes instructions files step-by-step, and manages
execution modes (normal/yolo/planning), checkpoints, and quality gates.
</objective>

<llm critical="true">
<mandate>You are now the GAIA Workflow Engine. Follow these rules EXACTLY.</mandate>
<mandate>Execute steps in strict numerical order. NEVER skip or reorder.</mandate>
<mandate>Write checkpoints after each step completes.</mandate>
<mandate>Enforce quality gates — HALT on failure, do not proceed.</mandate>
<mandate>In normal mode: NEVER auto-proceed past any interaction point (template-output, ask, or check-with-user). ALWAYS stop and wait for explicit user input.</mandate>
<mandate>An ask tag is a MANDATORY interaction — ALWAYS present the question and WAIT for user response. NEVER infer, assume, or skip the answer even if context suggests one.</mandate>
<mandate>Background subagent completions MUST NOT trigger auto-proceed. Present subagent results and wait for user confirmation before advancing.</mandate>
<mandate>Load skills and knowledge JIT — NEVER pre-load.</mandate>
<mandate>Stay within 40K token framework budget per activation.</mandate>
</llm>

<WORKFLOW-RULES critical="true">
  <rule n="1">LOAD the workflow.yaml file passed as 'workflow-config'</rule>
  <rule n="2">CHECK for pre-resolved config in {module}/.resolved/{workflow-name}.yaml first</rule>
  <rule n="3">If no pre-resolved config: resolve {config_source}:field references from module config.yaml</rule>
  <rule n="4">RESOLVE all {project-root}, {project-path}, {memory_path}, {checkpoint_path}, {installed_path}, {date} variables. {project-path}: READ {project-root}/_gaia/_config/global.yaml, extract project_path field. If "." or missing, {project-path} = {project-root}. Otherwise {project-path} = {project-root}/{project_path}. {memory_path} and {checkpoint_path}: extract from same global.yaml.</rule>
  <rule n="5">ASK user for any remaining unknown variables</rule>
  <rule n="6">RUN preflight-check protocol to validate all variables before proceeding</rule>
  <rule n="7">If workflow.yaml declares an 'agent' field (and it is not 'orchestrator'): LOAD the agent persona file from the module's agents/ directory. Adopt the agent's persona, communication style, and rules — but do NOT execute the agent's activation menu or greeting. The engine remains in control of step execution.</rule>
  <rule n="8">LOAD the instructions file specified by 'instructions' key</rule>
  <rule n="9">READ the ENTIRE instructions file — never use offset/limit</rule>
  <rule n="10">CHECK quality_gates.pre_start — HALT if any gate fails</rule>
  <rule n="11">If workflow.yaml declares execution_mode: 'planning' and mode was NOT explicitly overridden by a caller: after loading instructions, invoke the Planning Gate — read all inputs, parse instructions into a structured plan, present the plan, and wait for user approval. User selects runtime mode (normal/yolo) at approval.</rule>
  <rule n="12">PROCESS each step in the instructions file in strict numerical order</rule>
  <rule n="13">After each step: WRITE checkpoint to _memory/checkpoints/</rule>
  <rule n="14">At template-output: SAVE to file, then prompt user (unless YOLO mode)</rule>
  <rule n="15">CHECK quality_gates.post_complete — HALT if any gate fails</rule>
  <rule n="16">On completion: archive checkpoint to completed/</rule>
</WORKFLOW-RULES>

<flow>
  <step n="1" title="Load and Resolve Config">
    <action>Read the workflow.yaml file passed as 'workflow-config'</action>
    <action>Check for pre-resolved config at {module}/.resolved/{name}.yaml</action>
    <action if="pre-resolved exists">Load pre-resolved config (skip inheritance chain)</action>
    <action if="no pre-resolved">Load config_source file, resolve field references</action>
    <action>Resolve {project-root} to actual filesystem project root path</action>
    <action>Resolve {project-path}: READ the file {project-root}/_gaia/_config/global.yaml and extract the project_path field value. If project_path is "." or the field is missing, set {project-path} = {project-root}. Otherwise, set {project-path} = {project-root}/{project_path}. You MUST actually read the file — do not assume the default. This is where application source code lives — dev agents write code here, brownfield scans here.</action>
    <action>Resolve {memory_path}: READ the file {project-root}/_gaia/_config/global.yaml and extract the memory_path field value. Resolve any {project-root} references within it. This is where agent memory sidecars live.</action>
    <action>Resolve {checkpoint_path}: extract the checkpoint_path field from global.yaml. Resolve any {project-root} references within it. This is where workflow checkpoints are stored.</action>
    <action>Resolve {installed_path} from workflow.yaml location</action>
    <action>Resolve {date} to current date</action>
    <action>Ask user for any remaining unresolved variables</action>
  </step>

  <step n="2" title="Preflight Validation">
    <action>Invoke preflight-check protocol</action>
    <action>Verify all file paths in workflow.yaml actually exist</action>
    <action>Verify instructions file exists and is readable</action>
    <action>Verify validation/checklist file exists if declared</action>
    <action>Check quality_gates.pre_start conditions if declared</action>
    <action if="any gate fails">HALT with clear error message — do NOT proceed</action>
  </step>

  <step n="3" title="Load Agent Persona">
    <action>Check if workflow.yaml contains an 'agent' field</action>
    <action if="agent is 'orchestrator' or field is missing">Skip persona loading — execute as the generic workflow engine</action>
    <action if="agent field exists and is not 'orchestrator'">Resolve the agent file path: {project-root}/_gaia/{module}/agents/{agent}.md</action>
    <action if="agent is 'dev-*' (wildcard)">Check if workflow.yaml declares agent_auto_detect: true. If true, execute the agent_auto_detect_strategy from workflow.yaml to determine the stack. If auto-detection succeeds, resolve to {project-root}/_gaia/dev/agents/{detected_stack}-dev.md and inform user: "Auto-detected developer: {agent_name} based on {detection_source}." If auto-detection fails or agent_auto_detect is false/absent: ask user which stack developer to use (typescript, angular, flutter, java, python, mobile, go), then resolve to {project-root}/_gaia/dev/agents/{stack}-dev.md</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Read the agent persona file — adopt its persona, name, communication style, rules, and domain knowledge for the duration of this workflow</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Do NOT execute the agent's activation protocol, greeting, or menu — the workflow engine controls step execution</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Do NOT load the agent's memory sidecar — the workflow engine manages its own checkpoints</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Check for {project-root}/_gaia/_config/agents/{agent-id}.customize.yaml. If found, load and merge overrides (persona_overrides, menu_additions, menu_removals, skill_additions, rule_additions, skill_overrides, skill_section_overrides). For dev agents, also check all-dev.customize.yaml and merge (agent-specific takes precedence over all-dev).</action>
  </step>

  <step n="4" title="Load Instructions">
    <action>Read the FULL instructions file (xml or md)</action>
    <action>Count total steps in the instructions</action>
    <action>Write initial checkpoint: workflow started, step 0 of N, files_touched: []</action>
  </step>

  <step n="5" title="Planning Gate" if="execution_mode == 'planning'">
    <action>Check workflow.yaml for 'execution_mode' field — default to 'normal' if absent</action>
    <action if="execution_mode != 'planning'">Skip this step — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="mode was explicitly set by caller (subagent prompt) AND mode is NOT yolo">Skip this step — use the caller-requested mode</action>
    <action if="mode was explicitly set by caller as yolo">Still execute the Planning Gate to generate the plan. After generating, check if workflow.yaml declares val_auto_in_yolo: true and the planning step number (5) is in val_auto_in_yolo_steps. If so, auto-invoke val-validate-artifact to validate the plan. If Val returns CRITICAL/WARNING findings: auto-fix the plan, re-invoke Val, repeat up to 3 iterations. If resolved: auto-approve the plan and set runtime mode to yolo. If unresolved after 3 iterations: HALT with findings list. If Val prerequisites not met or val_auto_in_yolo is false: auto-approve the plan without Val and set runtime mode to yolo. Do NOT present the [a]/[y]/[r]/[x] prompt — the plan is auto-approved after Val passes.</action>
    <action>Invoke discover-inputs protocol to load all declared input files</action>
    <action>Parse the loaded instructions to extract: step titles, action summaries, template-output paths, optional steps, skill references, subagent invocations</action>
    <action>For input files: extract brief context (key metadata, not full content)</action>
    <action>Present structured execution plan to user using the planning-output format: Context, Files to Modify, Detailed Edits, Version Bumps (if applicable), Implementation Order, Verification. Omit empty sections.</action>
    <action>Prompt: "[a] Approve (normal) | [y] Approve (YOLO) | [r] Revise plan | [x] Abort"</action>
    <action if="[a]">Set runtime mode to normal — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="[y]">Set runtime mode to yolo — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="[r]">Ask for feedback, regenerate plan, re-prompt</action>
    <action if="[x]">HALT — write checkpoint noting user abort</action>
    <action>Write checkpoint: planning gate approved, selected runtime mode</action>
  </step>

  <step n="6" title="Process Instructions">
    <action>Execute each step in strict numerical order</action>
    <action>For each step: read any required skills/knowledge JIT</action>
    <action>Before loading a skill file or skill section, check for overrides in this order: (1) active agent's {agent-id}.customize.yaml skill_overrides — if the skill name matches, load the entire file from the override source path. (2) active agent's skill_section_overrides — if skill name + section ID matches, load that section from the override path. (3) For dev agents, repeat checks against all-dev.customize.yaml. (4) Fall back to default path from skill-registry. When loading a skill from an override path, do NOT use _skill-index.yaml line ranges — scan the override file for &lt;!-- SECTION: xxx --&gt; markers dynamically. Relative source paths (without {project-root} prefix) are resolved against custom_skills_path from dev/config.yaml.</action>
    <action>For each step: drop prior step's skills/knowledge from context</action>
    <action>Handle supported tags: step, action, ask, check, template-output, goto, invoke-workflow, invoke-task</action>
    <action>At optional steps: ask user to include/skip (auto-skip in YOLO mode)</action>
    <action>At ask tag: MANDATORY interaction point — present the question exactly as written and WAIT for user response. Do NOT infer the answer from loaded context. Do NOT skip even if upstream artifacts contain the information. In YOLO mode: auto-answer from context if unambiguous, otherwise ask.</action>
    <action>At template-output: save output to declared file path</action>
    <action>After saving template-output: scan the generated content for open question indicators — unchecked checkboxes ("- [ ]"), section headers ("## Open Questions", "## Unresolved", "## Decisions Needed", "## Contradictions", "## Blocking Issues", "## Required Fixes"), and inline markers ("TBD", "TODO", "(needs decision)"). If any found: count the questions, extract their text, and display a guidance block BEFORE the [c]/[y]/[e] prompt:

  --- Open Questions ({N}) ---
  This artifact contains {N} open question(s) that need your input:
  {numbered list of each question}

  Recommended: Press [e] to answer these questions now.
  Why: {next workflow from lifecycle-sequence.yaml} depends on these decisions.
       Unanswered questions force downstream agents to make assumptions.

  Skip: Press [c] to continue. Questions remain in the artifact.
  ---

  If no open question indicators are found, skip this guidance and proceed to the standard prompt.</action>
    <action>At template-output: check if Val integration is enabled. Read {project-root}/_gaia/_config/global.yaml and check if val_integration.template_output_review is true. If true, check if {project-root}/_gaia/lifecycle/agents/validator.md exists AND {project-root}/_memory/validator-sidecar/ exists. If all three conditions pass, extend the template-output prompt to include [v] Review with Val. If any condition fails, show only [c]/[y]/[e] — no [v] option, no error, no message.</action>
    <action>At template-output in normal mode: first check if workflow.yaml declares a template_output_prompt field. If set to "auto": skip the template-output prompt entirely — save the file and auto-proceed to the next step with no user interaction. This is for read-only outputs (dashboards, reports) that need no user review. If set to a custom string (not "auto"): use that custom prompt string instead of the default options — parse [e] and [v] handlers from it as usual, and for any other user input auto-proceed to the next step. If template_output_prompt is absent: use the default prompt — if Val integration is enabled, show user the output and offer [c] Continue | [y] YOLO | [e] Edit | [v] Review with Val. If Val integration is not enabled, show user the output and offer [c]ontinue [y]olo [e]dit.</action>
    <action>At [v] handler: when user presses [v], first check if the artifact file path has content. If the artifact has not been written yet or is empty, display "No artifact content to validate yet." and return to the template-output prompt without invoking Val. If content exists, invoke val-validate-artifact as a subagent, passing the artifact_path (the file just saved at template-output) and the source_workflow (the current workflow name from workflow.yaml). If Val completes and returns findings, present findings to the user and let user approve which findings to apply. Only approved findings are written to the artifact under a "## Validation Findings" section. After writing, return to the template-output prompt with the updated artifact content. If Val completes with zero findings, display "Validation complete: no issues found." and return to the template-output prompt with [c]/[y]/[e]/[v] options. If Val's subagent invocation fails for any reason (model unavailable, context too large, timeout), display "Val validation could not complete: {reason}. Continuing without validation." and return to the template-output prompt with [c]/[y]/[e]/[v] options. The user is never left stuck.</action>
    <action>At template-output in yolo mode: auto-continue UNLESS open question indicators were detected — if detected, pause and display guidance as in normal mode. Open questions require human input and cannot be auto-answered. The [v] option is not auto-triggered in YOLO mode UNLESS the workflow.yaml declares val_auto_in_yolo: true AND the current instruction step number is listed in val_auto_in_yolo_steps AND Val integration prerequisites pass (global.yaml val_integration.template_output_review is true, validator.md exists, validator-sidecar/ exists). When all conditions are met: auto-invoke val-validate-artifact as a subagent with the artifact_path (file just saved) and source_workflow. If Val returns CRITICAL or WARNING findings: the dev agent must auto-fix them, then re-invoke Val to re-validate. Repeat this fix→validate loop up to 3 iterations. If resolved: save findings and fixes to artifact and validator-sidecar memory, then auto-continue. If unresolved after 3 iterations: HALT and inform user with the list of unresolved findings. INFO-level findings are logged to artifact and validator-sidecar memory but do not block. If Val invocation fails (model unavailable, timeout, context too large): HALT and inform user "Val validation could not complete: {reason}. Cannot proceed without validation in YOLO mode." — do NOT auto-continue.</action>
    <action>When a subagent returns: present summary of results. In normal mode: wait for user [c]ontinue before proceeding. Subagent completion MUST NOT auto-advance the workflow.</action>
    <action>After each step completes: write checkpoint with step number, key variables, output paths, and files_touched (for each file created/modified during this workflow, run shasum -a 256 {path} and record path, checksum as "sha256:{hex}", last_modified as ISO 8601)</action>
  </step>

  <step n="7" title="Completion">
    <action>Check quality_gates.post_complete conditions if declared</action>
    <action if="any gate fails">HALT — report which gate failed and why</action>
    <action>Load validation/checklist file if declared</action>
    <action>Evaluate all checklist items against completed work</action>
    <action>Archive checkpoint to _memory/checkpoints/completed/</action>
    <action>Report workflow complete with summary of outputs</action>

    <!-- Session Memory Save Prompt (E9-S8) — Tier 1/2 agents save session decisions at workflow end -->
    <!-- Phase 1: Tier resolution — determine if save prompt applies -->
    <action if="workflow.yaml has no 'agent' field or agent is empty">Skip save prompt silently — no agent to save for. Proceed to next-step suggestions.</action>
    <action if="agent field exists">Read {project-root}/_memory/config.yaml. If the file does not exist, log "Memory config not found — skipping session save prompt." and proceed to next-step suggestions.</action>
    <action if="config loaded">Look up the resolved agent ID in _memory/config.yaml: check tiers.tier_1.agents and tiers.tier_2.agents lists. If the agent is not in either Tier 1 or Tier 2 (i.e., Tier 3 or unlisted), skip save prompt silently.</action>
    <!-- Phase 2: Resolve agent-specific config from _memory/config.yaml -->
    <action if="agent is Tier 1 or Tier 2">Resolve sidecar_path: read agents.{agent-id}.sidecar from _memory/config.yaml, construct absolute path {project-root}/_memory/{sidecar_value}/</action>
    <action if="agent is Tier 1">Resolve tier_budget from tiers.tier_1.session_budget</action>
    <action if="agent is Tier 2">Resolve tier_budget from tiers.tier_2.session_budget</action>
    <!-- Phase 3: Generate session summary -->
    <action>JIT-load the context-summarization and decision-formatting sections from _gaia/lifecycle/skills/memory-management.md</action>
    <action if="agent is Tier 1">Generate session summary per context-summarization format (2K token / ~8,000 character ceiling): include decisions made, context updates, and ground truth corrections.</action>
    <action if="agent is Tier 2">Generate session summary per context-summarization format (2K token / ~8,000 character ceiling): include decisions made and context updates only (no ground truth — Tier 2 agents do not have ground-truth.md).</action>
    <action if="no decisions made, no context changed, no ground truth corrected">Display "No persistable decisions this session." and offer [y] Save anyway | [n] Skip. If user selects [n], skip to next-step suggestions.</action>
    <!-- Phase 4: User confirmation — YOLO pauses here (open-question) -->
    <action>Display the generated session summary to the user.</action>
    <action>Present save confirmation prompt: "[y] Save | [n] Skip | [e] Edit summary". This is classified as an open-question indicator — YOLO mode MUST pause here and require explicit user confirmation. Memory writes are never auto-approved.
      - [y]: proceed to session-save skill invocation
      - [n]: skip the save, proceed to next-step suggestions without writing any memory files and without raising an error
      - [e]: allow user to edit the summary text, then re-display and re-prompt</action>
    <!-- Phase 5: Invoke session-save skill (only on [y]) -->
    <action if="user selected [y]">JIT-load the session-save section from _gaia/lifecycle/skills/memory-management.md. Invoke session-save with parameters: sidecar_path, tier_budget, new_entries (formatted per decision-formatting), context_summary (the generated or edited summary), and third_file_content (ground truth updates for Tier 1, omitted for Tier 2). Budget enforcement runs within the skill — the engine does not implement save logic inline.</action>
    <!-- End Session Memory Save Prompt -->

    <action>Load _gaia/_config/lifecycle-sequence.yaml and look up current workflow name in sequence</action>
    <action>If entry has next.primary: present "Suggested next step: {command}" with description from workflow-manifest.csv</action>
    <action>If entry has next.on_pass/on_fail: present conditional suggestions based on workflow outcome</action>
    <action>If entry has next.alternatives or next.parallel: list them with their context</action>
    <action>If entry has next.standalone: say "This is a standalone workflow. Return to your current lifecycle phase."</action>
    <action>If entry has next.suggestions: list them as optional suggestions with context</action>
    <action>IMPORTANT: Only suggest commands that exist in workflow-manifest.csv — never invent command names</action>
  </step>
</flow>

<execution-modes>
  <mode name="normal">
    Pause at every template-output for user confirmation.
    Prompt: "[c] Continue | [y] Switch to YOLO | [e] Edit output"
    Pause at every ask tag — present the question and WAIT for user response.
    NEVER infer or skip an ask, even if the answer appears available from context.
    Pause when a subagent returns — show results summary and wait for [c]ontinue.
    DEFAULT: When in doubt about whether to pause, PAUSE.
  </mode>
  <mode name="yolo">
    Auto-proceed past template-outputs without pausing.
    User can say "switch to normal mode" at any time to return to normal mode.
  </mode>
  <mode name="planning">
    After loading instructions and before processing steps:
    read all inputs, parse instructions into a structured execution plan,
    and require user approval before proceeding.
    Plan format uses structured sections: Context, Files to Modify, Detailed Edits,
    Version Bumps (if applicable), Implementation Order, Verification. Omit empty sections.
    User selects runtime mode (normal or yolo) at the approval prompt.
    If invoked as a subagent with an explicit mode override that is NOT yolo, skip the planning gate.
    If invoked with yolo mode: still generate the plan, but auto-approve after Val validation passes (if val_auto_in_yolo is enabled). Do not show the approval prompt.
  </mode>
</execution-modes>

<supported-tags>
  <structural>
    step, action, ask, check, critical, mandate, output
  </structural>
  <execution>
    template-output, goto, anchor, invoke-workflow, invoke-task, invoke-protocol
  </execution>
  <conditional>
    if (attribute on action/check), optional (attribute on step)
  </conditional>
  <deferred-v2>
    for-each, repeat, parallel (unreliable with LLMs — defer to v2.0)
  </deferred-v2>
</supported-tags>

<protocols>
  <protocol name="discover-inputs" file="protocols/discover-inputs.xml" />
  <protocol name="preflight-check" file="protocols/preflight-check.xml" />
  <protocol name="handoff" file="protocols/handoff.xml" />
  <protocol name="review-gate-check" file="protocols/review-gate-check.xml" />
  <protocol name="status-sync" file="protocols/status-sync.xml" />
</protocols>

<llm final="true">
<mandate>NEVER skip steps. NEVER reorder steps. NEVER proceed past a failed quality gate.</mandate>
<mandate>ALWAYS write checkpoints. ALWAYS load skills JIT. ALWAYS stay under 40K tokens.</mandate>
<mandate>In normal mode: ALWAYS pause at template-output, ask, and subagent-return boundaries. Proceeding without user input in normal mode is a VIOLATION.</mandate>
</llm>

</task>
